Henry Mattson Papers
Syracuse University 222 Waverly Ave Syracuse, NY 13244
Henry Mattson Papers
1933-1964
Syracuse University 222 Waverly Ave Syracuse, NY 13244
Mattson, Henry E. (Henry Elis), 1887-1971
0.5 linear ft
Swedish-American painter. Collection contains clippings, correspondence, printed material, subject files, photographs, drawings, manuscripts and articles.
3166090
Biographical History
Henry Mattson (1887-1971) was a Swedish-American painter known for his seascapes, nocturnal scenes and figures. Born in Gothenburg, Sweden, Mattson emigrated to the United States in 1906. Mattson began painting in 1912, while working in a machine shop in Worcester, Massachusetts. He moved to Woodstock, New York in 1916 and developed a distinctive style through being almost entirely self-taught. In the 1930s and 1940s, Mattson’s career began to flourish, winning awards and wider recognition.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Henry Mattson Papers are divided into five series. Clippings include both newsprint and magazine articles related to Mattson's work. Correspondence is a mixture of personal and professional letters, often congratulating Mattson on accomplishments or negotiating the purchase of a work of art. Memorabilia are a collection of photos, receipts, self-portraits, and other materials. Publications are a collection of full publications featuring articles on Mattson's work. Writings include autobiographical materials written for address or broadcast.
Arrangement of the Collection
Materials are alphabetically arranged by topic or format. Publications are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Mattson, Henry E. (Henry Elis), 1887-1971.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.); Woodstock (N.Y.).; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Sketches.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Henry Mattson, 1964.
Inventory
- Clippings
  - Magazine, 1934-1940; 1943-1946,; 1956,; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper, 1942-1953; 1956,; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1933-1945; 1948-1953,; 1964,; undated; letters received by Mattson, mostly written in praise of his work or in congratulation for awards he received (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1941-1942; 1945,; 1949-1956,; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, contains newspaper clippings (Oversize 1)
  - Self-portraits, includes original sketches, photographs, and negatives (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - World's Fair materials, relating to Mattson’s participation in the international “Wall of Fame” in the 1940 New York World’s Fair (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Note about collection, contract for painting Portland, Maine Post Office mural, invitation to 75th anniversary of the MET, certificate of identification for traveling in Sweden, 2 post cards from Portland, Maine and photographs of 2 paintings.
- Publications
  - Carnegie Magazine, Oct 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Magazine of Art, May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Art Digest, Aug 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Artist, Nov 1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica Collection of Contemporary American Painting, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Paintings of the Year, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - American Swedish Monthly, Mar 1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Writings
  - Radio transcript, 1935 Oct (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Autobiography in Swedish and English, Mar 1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)